[Music]
why are vegetarian diets so effective in
preventing and treating diabetes maybe
it's because of the weight loss those
eating more plant-based tend to be
significantly Slimmer and not just based
on like looking at a cross-section of
the population but you can do
Interventional trials and put it to the
test a randomized controll community-
based trial of a whole food plant-based
diet the key difference between
plant-based nutrition and other
approaches to weight loss is that
participants were formed to eat the
whole food plant-based that add libidum
meaning eat as much as you want no
calorie counting no portion control just
eat it's about improving the quality of
food rather than restricting the
quantity of food and then in this study
they had people just you know focus on
diet rather than increasing exercise
just because they wanted to isolate out
the effects of eating healthier so what
happened no restrictions on portions eat
all the healthy foods you want here's
where they started out on average obese
at nearly 210 PBS the average height was
about 5'5 3 months in they were down
about 18 lbs 6 months in more like 26
lbs down but you know how these weight
loss trials go I mean this wasn't an
instant institutional study where they
like you know locked people up and fed
them you know no meals were provided
they just informed people about the
benefits of plant-based D encourage them
to you know do it in their own lives
their own families and their own homes
and communities and so you know yeah
typically what you see in these
so-called Free Living studies is that
you know weight loss at six months uh
but then by a year the weight creeps
back or even worse but in this study
they're able to maintain that weight
loss all year and of course their you
know cholesterol got better too but
their claim to fame is that they
achieved greater weight loss at 6 and 12
months than any other trial that does
not limit calorie intake or mandate
regular exercise that's worth repeating
a whole food plant-based diet achieved
the greatest weight loss ever recorded
at 6 and 12 months compared to any other
such intervention published in the
medical literature now obviously with
you know very low calorie starvation
diets you can drop people down to any we
however these medically supervised
liquid diets are obviously just you know
short-term fixes associated with high
cost High attrition rates and high
probability of regaining most of the
weight whereas the whole point of Whole
Food plant-based nutrition is to
maximize long-term Health and Longevity
I mean even if for example you know low
carb D were as effective the point of
weight loss is not to fit into a
skinnier casket studies on the effects
of low carbohydrate diets have shown
higher rates of all cause mortality
meaning a shorter lifespan decreased
artery function worsening of coronary AR
disease and increased rates of
constipation headaches bad breath muscle
cramps General weakness and rash and yet
still not as effective as the diet that
actually has all the good side effects
like decreasing risk of diabetes Beyond
just the weight loss yes the lower risk
of type 2 diabetes among vegetarians may
be explained in part by improved weight
state is however the lower risk Also may
be explained by higher amounts of
ingested dietary fiber and plant protein
the absence of meat and egg derived
protein and heem iron and lower intake
of saturated fat most studies report the
lowest risk of type 2 diabetes among
those who adhere to strictly plant-based
diets this may be explained by the fact
that vegans in contrast to vegetarians
do not eat eggs which appear to be
linked to higher diabetes risk maybe
it's you eating lower on the food chain
so avoid the highest levels of
persistent organic pollutants like
dioxins pcbs DDT and animal products
which have been implicated as a diabetes
risk factor maybe has to do with the gut
microbiome with all that fiber no
surprise that there'd be less disease
causing bugs and more protective gut
floor which can lead to less
inflammation throughout the body that
may be the key feature linking the
healthier gut with beneficial health
effects including the metabolic
dysfunction you can see in type 2
diabetes and it's that mult multiplicity
of benefits that can help with
compliance and family Buy in you know
whereas a household that includes people
who do not have diabetes maybe unlikely
to enthusiastically follow a quotequote
diabetic diet a healthy diet is not
disease specific and it can improve
other chronic conditions too so while
the diabetic patient will likely see
Improvement in their blood sugar control
a spouse suffering from constipation or
high blood pressure may also see
improvements as May overweight children
if you make healthy eating a family
[Music]
affair